Oliver Tambo Papers 2000.0144
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
- Series C: Special Topics
  - Individuals (Box C3)
    - David and Norma Kitson (Box C3., Folder 8)
      - Photographs (9 items) (Box C3., Folder 8.5)
        24 Hour Picket outside South Africa House.
    - Albert J. Luthuli (Box C3., Folder 9)
      - Commemorative Speech on July 21, date of Chief Luthuli’s death
      - Miscellaneous item--Slip attached to payment forwarded to A. J. Luthuli ( BBC transcription service)
    - Johnny Makatini (Box C3., Folder 10)
      - List of various organisations/countries who sent messages on the death of Johnny Makhatini, 1988 December 5
      - Programme for the Funeral of Johnny Makhatini
      - Pamphlet "Obituary - Johnstone "Johnny" Mfanafuthi Makatini (Tireless Freedom Fighter)
    - Nelson Mandela (Box C3., Folder 11)
      - Correspondence (Box C3., Folder 11.1)
        - Letters written from Pollsmoor Prison (27 items including duplicates), undated, 1978-1989
      - Report - Robben Island, 1970 January (Box C3., Folder 11.2)
      - Correspondence (4 items), 1990 (Box C3., Folder 11.3)
      - Speeches and Statements (14 items), 1964, 1985-1991 (Box C3., Folder 11.4)
      - Published Speeches and Statements (10 items) (Box C3., Folder 11.5)
      - Itinerary(s) and Programmes (Box C3., Folder 11.6)
      - Miscellaneous Items--Postcard, Card, Photograph (Box C3., Folder 11.7)
      - Drafts of Plays/Books on Nelson Mandela (6 items) (Box C3., Folder 11.8)
        - Mary Benson's book on Nelson Mandela (Box C3., Folder 11.8.1)
        - What is to be done - A play by Laurie C. Sain, Includes correspondence, 1985 (Box C3., Folder 11.8.2)
      - Report/Memorandum on meetings with Nelson Mandela whilst in Prison (2 items) (Box C3., Folder 11.9)
        - Items include An account of a meeting with Nelson Mandela by Nicholas Bethell, 1985 Janaury 27
      - Biographical Notes on Nelson Mandela (Box C3., Folder 11.1)
      - Speeches given in honour of Nelson Mandela (5 items) (Box C3., Folder 11.11)
      - International Support (Box C3., Folder 11.12)
        - Correspondence, Reports and Miscellaneous Items
        - Messages of Solidarity received on the occasion of Nelson Mandela’s 60th Birthday, 23 July 1978; Message from Willy Brandt to Nelson Mandela on latter’s Birthday, 1986/Pamphlet - 70th birthday greetings
        - International Calls for Mandela’s Release and Awards
        - Survey of Events and Actions in Honour of and for the Release of Nelson Mandela, Preliminary results prepared by the British Anti-Apartheid Movement, 1984 October
        - Nelson Mandela Park - Welford Road, Leicester (Information Package)
        - Freedom of the City of Aberdeen
        - International Reception Committee Memorandum; Nelson Mandela British Honours List (April 1990); Statements (Including statement on release of Nelson Mandela); Publication - IRC News (Box C3., Folder 11.12.1)
        - Responses to his release from prison (Includes a statement by Oliver Tambo) (18 items) (Box C3., Folder 11.12.2)
          Items include Statements by O. J. Masire, PLO, Communist Party/ Sweden, People’s Republic of Bulgaria.
      - ANC - Miscellaneous (Box C3., Folder 11.13)
        - Correspondence, Reports and Paper (4 items)
          Paper, "What is the Significance of Nelson Mandela’s 70th Birthday for the ANC"; Telexes/Notes re Libyan embassy's offer to rebuild house of the Mandela's, 1988.
      - Media Reports/Comments (Box C3., Folder 11.14)
      - Miscellaneous (Includes list of items forwarded to Nelson Mandela), 1990 March 25 (Box C3., Folder 11.15)
    - Winnie Mandela (Box C3., Folder 12)
      - Correspondence (3 items), 1986 April (Box C3., Folder 12.1)
        Includes correspondence addressed to Oliver Tambo.
      - Transcript, " Winnie Mandela and the Football Club," A File on 4 Special Documentary (Box C3., Folder 12.2)
      - Press Cutting, Winnie Mandela in Brandfort, Fatima Meer (Index on Censorship) (Box C3., Folder 12.3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box C3., Folder 12.4)
        - Postcard with a portrait of Winnie Mandela
        - Notes on Winnie Mandela
    - J. B. Marks (Box C3., Folder 13)
      - Correspondence (1 item), 1969 November 24
        Addressed to J. B. Marks, London ( Yusef Dadoo?).
      - Address, Opening address by J. B. Marks at The Morogoro Consultative Conference of the ANC, 3p. Ms.
      - Record of Exchange of Messages re death of J. B. Marks
      - Obituary, In Memory of J. B. Marks, Provisional Headquarters, Morogoro, ANC
    - Govan Mbeki (Box C3., Folder 14)
      - Speeches
        - Canon Collins Memorial Lecture delivered by Govan Mbeki, London, 1990 September 27
        - Address to the Govan Mbeki Fellowship at the University of Amsterdam, 1990 September 28
        - Publications (2 items)
          Includes Govan Mbeki, An Honorary Doctor behind bars.
    - Thabo Mbeki (Box C3., Folder 15)
      - General Correspondence (33 items), 1978-1986 (Box C3., Folder 15.1)
      - Speeches and Statements (4 items) (Box C3., Folder 15.2)
        - "Domestic and Foreign Policies of a New South Africa," Lecture given by Thabo Mbeki (Conflict and Change in Southern Africa: Scandinavian and Canadian Perspectives and Policy Options, [Translation in French], 1978 February 19 - 22
        - Statement by Thabo Mbeki on Poverty and Change in South Africa: Duke University, Durham, 1989 February 16
      - Miscellaneous Questions for an interview (Box C3., Folder 15.3)
    - Mzala Nxumalo (Box C3., Folder 16)
      - "Education for Revolution: The Role of a Qualified Cadre in our struggle"
      - Death of Mzala Nxumalo, Brian Bunting, London, 1991 February 23
    - Jeannette Schoon, 1949 - 1984 (Box C3., Folder 17)
      - Pamphlet, Published by ADAC
    - Albertina Sisulu (Box C3., Folder 18)
      - Correspondence with Albertina Sisulu from The White House and Danielle Mitterrand, 1989 May 11 and February 20
    - Walter Sisulu (Box C3., Folder 19)
      - Address by Walter Sisulu at the National Welcome Back Rally, Johannesburg, 1989 October 29
      - Biographical Notes
      - Publication, Walter Max Ulyate Sisulu, Published by Southern Africa - The Imprisoned Society in cooperation with the UN Centre against Apartheid
    - Joe Slovo (Box C3., Folder 20)
      - Address, "Prospects for Armed Struggle in South Africa," National Student Conference, Revolution in Southern Africa, Oxford, 1968 March 9 (Folder 179)
      - Press Cuttings (2 items)
        Items include:"What Recent 'Peace' Initiatives Mean," Radio Freedom (Addis Ababa) Interviews with Joe Slovo.
  - Organizations (Box C4)
    - Africa Fund (Action for Resisting Invasion, Colonialism and Apartheid) (Box C4., Folder 1)
      - Final Documents - Africa Fund Summit, New Delhi, 1987 January
      - Circular with enclosed educational materials concerning Health, produced in cooperation with the Committee for Health in southern Africa ( CHISA)
    - Afrikaanseweerstandbeweging ( AWB), 1991 (Box C4., Folder 2)
      - Correspondence from Mendi Msimang (Chief Representative, ANC Mission - UK and Ireland) re AWB recruitment
      - Miscellaneous, "To all members of the Afrikaner Volk!"
    - Afro-Asian People's Solidarity Organisation (Box C4., Folder 3)
      - Booklet, International Seminar on Agricultural Development and Food Security in the Developing Countries, Hungary, 1985 October 13 - 17
      - Afro-Asian Solidarity (A Quarterly issued by the Afro-Asian Peoples Solidarity Organization), Nos. 3-4, 1989
    - American Committee on Africa (Box C4., Folder 4)
      - Press Release, "Court rules for hearing on ACOA against the New York Times for South African Job Advertisements,", 1973 November 26
      - Action News (4 items), 1988-1991
      - Pamphlets (6 items)
        Items include Observe Human Rights Day, December 10, by answering this appeal for action against apartheid (circa 1950s/1960s); Join the Free South Africa Movement; Question and Answers on Divestment; Programme - Reception honouring Oliver Tambo, 22 January 1987 (American Committee on Africa/Africa Fund).
    - Anglo American (Box C4., Folder 5)
      - Reports
        - Anglo American Policy on South Africa as reported by Clem Sutner
        - Summary of lecture by Clem Sutner, Delivered in Harare, 1989 February (Folder 204)
      - Pamphlet, "Reform and Reaction in South Africa," G. W. H. Relly (Address to the South Africa Club, London, 1981 October 8
    - Anti Apartheid Movement (Box C4., Folder 6)
      - Ireland (Box C4., Folder 6.1)
        - Correspondence (2 items), 1990
          Correspondents Kader and Louise Asmal.
        - Resolutions, 1972
        - Publications
          - Annual Report, 1989-1990
          - Pamphlet, "The Dunnes Strike and the Struggle against Apartheid,", 1985 April
      - France (5 items), 1980, 1984 (Box C4., Folder 6.2)
        - Reaction to proposed visit of P. W. Botha by Comit contre le Colonialisme et l’Apartheid
        - Publication, 1977
      - Netherlands (Box C4., Folder 6.3)
        - Correspondence (1 item), 1983
          Correspondent Connie Braam.
      - United Kingdom (Box C4., Folder 6.4)
        - Correspondence (5 items), 1988-1991 (Box C4., Folder 6.4.1)
        - Minutes/Report (Box C4., Folder 6.4.2)
          - Minutes of the National Committee Meeting, House of Commons, 1964 March 25
          - Report of the Executive Committee to the National Committee, 1964 July 6
        - Memoranda (2 items) (Box C4., Folder 6.4.3)
          - Addressed to the ANC and other organisations from IAEA and Mike Terry, Executive Secretary, AAM)
        - Memoranda, Reports and Papers (6 items) (Box C4., Folder 6.4.4)
          - Memorandum to the United Nations Special Committee on the Policies of Apartheid of the Government of the RSA, London, 1964 April
            - " South Africa - Aspects of Foreign Investment and Finance," prepared by Vella Pillay, Meeting of the UN Special Committee on Apartheid, Dublin, 1974 May 21
            - National Convention against Apartheid and for Freedom in Namibia and South Africa, Draft Programme of Action, 1984 June 23 - 24
            - "Southern Africa - The Time to Choose," Progress Report, 1982
            - Constrained by Sanctions - The Apartheid Economy in 1988, A memorandum for Presentation to the Commonwealth Foreign Ministers Committee on Southern Africa, Harare, 1989 February 6
        - Press Releases and Statements (6 items) (Box C4., Folder 6.4.5)
          Includes Media Package: Nelson Mandela - Freedom at 70.
        - Publications (Box C4., Folder 6.4.6)
          - Annual Report of Activities and Developments (5items), 1977-1978, 1982-1986 (Box C4., Folder 6.4.6.1)
          - Members Newsletter (1 item), 1973 February
          - Anti Apartheid News (6 items), 1977, 1980, 1981, 1984 (Box C4., Folder 6.4.6.2)
          - General Items (10 items) (Box C4., Folder 6.4.6.3)
            Includes Southern Africa: The Time to Choose; Selling Out to Apartheid: British Government Support for Trade with South Africa; Apartheid Gold.
        - Pamphlets (10 items) (Box C4., Folder 6.4.7)
      - World Campaign (Box C4., Folder 6.5)
        - Correspondence, Reports and Publications (10 items)
          Includes World Campaign against Military and Nuclear Collaboration with South Africa and Bulletin of the Continuation Committee of the World Conference against Apartheid, Racism and Colonialism in Southern Africa.
    - Anti-Imperialist Solidarity Committee for Africa/Asia/Latin America (14 items) (Box C4., Folder 7)
      - Memoranda, Statements, Appeals and Publications
    - Artists against Apartheid (Sun City) (Box C4., Folder 8)
      - Correspondence between Steven Little (President) and the ANC, 1989 July 26
    - Association of West European Parliamentarians for Action against Apartheid ( AWEPAA) (8 items) (Box C4., Folder 9)
      - Statements, Report and Publications
    - Black Consciousness Movement of South Africa, London (Box C4., Folder 10)
      - Circular, Circular on the London Office
      - Publication, Solidarity, Volume 1, No. 2
    - Black Consciousness Movements (BCM (A)), Canada (Box C4., Folder 11)
      - Newsletter, 1983 January - February
    - Bophelo/Impilo Community Association (Box C4., Folder 12)
      - Constitution
      - Report, Presentation to 1990 Federation Conference - Jersey
      - Fifth Annual Report, Community Development in a Changing South Africa, 1989-1990
    - Centre for Development Studies, University of the Western Cape (Box C4., Folder 13)
      - Correspondence, Memoranda, Reports, Pamphlet
        - Report, 1990 July - 1991 March
        - Correspondence/Memoranda re temporary suspension of all CDS activities (2 items)
        - Memorandum, Meeting between ANC, UDF, COSATU, SASPRO and CDS (Board of Trustees), 1990 June 10
        - Discussion Document on Structures and Principles of a Constitution for a Democratic South Africa, Sent to Oliver Tambo by Zola Skweyiya, 1991 April 11
        - Pamphlet, CDS
    - Centre for Intergroup Studies (Box C4., Folder 14)
      - Pamphlet
    - Coalition for a Free Africa, Inc. (Box C4., Folder 15)
      - Proposed Fundraising Telethon - "From Selma to Soweto,", 1986
      - Information Package, Organisation of Telethon, 1987
    - Commonwealth (Box C4., Folder 16)
      - Statements, Press Releases, Publications (7 items), 1985, 1989-1990
        - Commonwealth News Release, Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, 1989 October 18 - 24
        - Responding to Reform: The phased lifting of Commonwealth sanctions against South Africa, 1991
        - Publication, Nassau Communiqué, 1985 October
    - Commonwealth EPG (4 items) (Box C4., Folder 17)
      - Press Release, Statement by the Secretary of State for External Affairs, Joe Clark, MP, 1986 June 12
      - Mission to South Africa: The Commonwealth Report, 1986
    - Congress of South African Students (COSAS) (Box C4., Folder 18)
      - Papers and Reports (2 items), undated
    - Congress of South African Trade Unions (COSATU) (Box C4., Folder 19)
      - List, Correspondence (17 items)
        - Meeting between UDF/ COSATU and Inkatha, 1989
        - Pamphlet, UWUSA or COSATU ... The People Choose! Issued by the National Student Federation
    - Congress of Traditional Leaders of South Africa ( CONTRALESA) (Box C4., Folder 20)
      - Reports and Speeches (3 items)
        - 1st National Conference to mark the launch of CONTRALESA, Broederstroom, 1990 September 28 - 30
        - Paper submitted at the Consultative Conference of the ANC, 1990 December 14
      - Pamphlets (2 items) (Box C4., Folder 20)
    - European Community (5 items) (Box C4., Folder 21)
      - Includes "A Code for Misconduct? A critical study of the implementation of the EEC Code of Conduct by British Companies operating in South Africa," Barbara Rodgers ( Christian Concern for Southern Africa), 1980
    - Inkatha (Box C4., Folder 22)
      - Mangosuthu G. Buthelezi: (Box C4., Folder 22.1)
        - Correspondence with Oliver Tambo re Oliver Tambo’s reaction to violence in Lamontville, 1984 (Box C4., Folder 22.1.1)
        - Speeches and Statements (Box C4., Folder 22.1.2)
          - 1977 (16 items) (Box C4., Folder 22.1.2a)
          - 1978 (10 items) (Box C4., Folder 22.1.2b)
          - 1979, 1990 July - November (21 items) (Box C4., Folder 22.1.2c)
        - Meetings between Mangosuthu G. Buthelezi and government officials (Box C4., Folder 22.1.3)
          - Conference of eight black leaders with B. J. Vorster and M. C. Botha, 1975 January 22
          - Meeting between M. G. Buthelezi and J. T. Kruger, Union Buildings, (Transcript), 1977 September 19
          - The Aide-Memoire used at the first meeting between the Prime Minister of South Africa, P. W. Botha and M. G. Buthelezi, 1979 January 22
        - Interview transcripts with Mangosuthu G. Buthelezi: (Box C4., Folder 22.1.4)
          - NBC Report, 1977 July 27
          - Interview given by M. G. Buthelezi to Chege Mbitiru, Foreign Editor, The Daily Nation, Kenya, Durban, 1977 August 13 (Folder 315)
        - Reports (Box C4., Folder 22.1.5)
          - Points made during an interview with Mangosuthu Buthulezi conducted by Voice of America, 1979 September 9
          - Oliver Tambo’s notes on Gatsha Buthulezi, Ms. 17p.
      - Inkatha (Box C4., Folder 22.2)
        - Correspondence (Miscellaneous, 4 items) (Box C4., Folder 22.2.1)
        - Statements (Box C4., Folder 22.2.2)
          - "The People’s Struggle," M. G. Buthelezi, London, personal copy sent to Oliver Tambo, 1979 October
          - Joint Statement arising out of a meeting between ANC and Inkatha, Issued by the ANC Department of Information and Publicity, 1990 September 19
          - Joint Statement of the IFP/ ANC meeting, Durban, 1991 January 29
        - Miscellaneous Memorandum/reaction to remarks by Buthelezi on Indians (letters/pamphlet)/Notes on Inkatha (Box C4., Folder 22.2.3)
        - Summary of Sibusiso M. Bengu’s Address, "The Role of Inkatha and the Youth in the Black Liberation Struggle in South Africa", Ulundi, 1978 (Box C4., Folder 22.2.4)
        - Publications/Pamphlets (10 items) (Box C4., Folder 22.2.5)
          - Inkatha, Vol. 1, No.1; Vol. 1 No.3; Vol.1, No.4; Vol.1, No.7, 1976-1979
          - Fourth Ordinary General Conference, 1978 July
          - Fifth Ordinary General Conference, 1979 June - July
          - Pamphlet, "Defend Your Rights - Stay South African"
          - Pamphlet, "Seek Your Rights as a South African"
        - Miscellaneous items relating to Natal (Box C4., Folder 22.2.6)
          - "Natal - The killing fields of apartheid," issued by Nusas- SRC Projects and SANSCO
          - Natal/Kwazulu, A selection of four papers from a conference on Co-operation for Development, presented by the Development Society of Southern Africa, 1985 August 5
    - International Committee against Racism Colonialism and Imperialism in Southern Africa (1 item) (Box C4., Folder 23)
      - Minutes, 1986 May 15
    - International Confederation of Free Trade Unions ( ICTFU) (Box C4., Folder 24)
      - Reports and Documents re ICTFU Delegation to South Africa (2 items), 1986
    - International Defence and Aid Fund ( IDAF) (Box C4., Folder 25)
      - Miscellaneous Correspondence, Statement (Box C4., Folder 25.1)
        - Correspondence between Horst Kleinschmidt and Ethel de Keyser re the publication of books and pamphlets by BDAF, 1985 April
        - Extract from Memorandum submitted to Dr. Nkrumah by Canon Collins, "South Africa: Refugees and Relief Work"
      - Report/Proposal (Box C4., Folder 25.2)
        Includes Proposal, "Project for Prisoners of Apartheid and Racism"
      - Publications (Box C4., Folder 25.3)
        - South Africa Freedom Call, Vol.1, No.5, 1960 August
        - i.d.a.f. news notes, 1982 December, 1983 June
      - Pamphlets and Cards (Box C4., Folder 25.4)
        - New titles/releases
        - 8 Post Cards, Women in Apartheid South Africa
      - Southern Africa Information Service, 1973 July - December (Box C4., Folder 25.5)
    - Institute for a Democratic Alternative for South Africa ( IDASA) (Box C4., Folder 26)
      - Statements
        - Statement by IDASA Delegation on their visit to the USSR, 1989 April 1 - 10
        - Joint Communiqué: Soviet Afro-Asian Solidarity Committee and IDASA, 1989 April
    - Institute for International Relations (Bonn) (Box C4., Folder 27)
      - Briefing Paper
        - 1984 - 1987 (Box C4., Folder 27.1)
        - 1988 (Box C4., Folder 27.2)
    - Inyandza National Movement (Also see: Countries - South Africa/'Independent States'/Homelands: Kangwane) (Box C4., Folder 28)
      - Report, "Estimates of Revenue and Expenditure for the year ending 31 December 1986"
      - Miscellaneous Agenda, Meeting between Inyandza delegation and ANC
    - Jubilee Trust (Box C4., Folder 29)
      - Unitry and Federal Forms of Transition, Jeremy Ive, 1987 October - November
      - "The Implications for future constitutional settlement in South Africa of recent and prospective developments in the structures of central government," Jeremy Ive and John Ashcroft, 1988 February
      - "Alternative strategies to overcome low income white fears of unemployment," Michael Schluter and David Porteous, 1988 February
    - Lawyers for Human Rights (Box C4., Folder 30)
      - Representation to The South African Law Commission on a Bill of Rights for South Africa, 1990 January
      - Lawyers for Human Rights and Death Squads in South Africa
    - National African Federated Chamber of Commerce ( NAFCOC) (Box C4., Folder 31)
      - Agenda
      - Statement, Joint Communiqué of the Meeting of NAFCOC and ANC, Lusaka, 1986 May 27
      - Press Release re meeting between delegation from NAFCOC led by its President, Dr. S. M. Motsuenyane and Geoffrey Howe, Pretoria, 1986 July 24
    - National Conference of Black Lawyers (Box C4., Folder 32)
      - Activities Report, 1972 December 1
      - Pamphlet
    - National Peace Accord ( South Africa) (Box C4., Folder 33)
      - Media Package (5 items)
    - National Seoposengwe Party (Box C4., Folder 35)
      - Paper, Tabled by the Secretariat at a Special Conference of the Party, Huhgudi/Vryburg, 1984 April 28 - 29
      - Statements/Resolutions
        - Challenges and Tasks ahead, 1990 December 10
        - Statement of Aims and Principles
    - New England Circle (Box C4., Folder 36)
      - Bulletin
        - 1989-1990
        - 1990-1991
      - Pamphlet, Includes extract on Oliver Tambo, Parker House, Boston, Massachusetts, 1985 April 30
    - Organisation of African Unity (Box C4., Folder 37)
      - 1963-1973 (Box C4., Folder 37.1)
        - General Report covering OAU activities, 1963-1973 (Box C4., Folder 37.1.1)
        - Report of the Administrative Secretary-General, 1968-1972 (Box C4., Folder 37.1.2)
        - Administrative Secretary Generals Reports of the OAU to Botswana, 1968 June 9 - 24 (Box C4., Folder 37.1.3)
        - Statement by Olajide Alo ( Nigeria), Rapporteur, at the 118th Meeting of The Special Committee on the Policies of Apartheid of the Government of the Republic of South Africa, 1969 June 26 (Box C4., Folder 37.1.4)
        - Memorandum submitted by ZAPU/ ANC Alliance to Heads of State on occasion of 6th Summit Meeting of OAU, 1969 (Box C4., Folder 37.1.5)
      - 1971 (Box C4., Folder 37.2)
        - Council of Ministers - 16th Ordinary Session, Addis Ababa, 1971 February - March
        - Council of Ministers - 17th Ordinary Session, Addis Ababa, 1971 June
      - 1972-1973 (Box C4., Folder 37.3)
        - Report of the Administrative Secretary General, 1972 June - May
      - 1973 (Box C4., Folder 37.4)
        - Minutes of the Meeting with the Representatives of the Liberation Movements on the preparations for 10th Anniversary of OAU, 1973 February 23 (Box C4., Folder 37.4.1)
          - International Conference of Experts for the Support of Victims of Colonialism and Apartheid in Southern Africa, Oslo, Norway, 1973 April 9 - 14
        - Report of the 21st Ordinary Session of the Co-ordinating Committee for the Liberation of Africa to the 20th Session of the Council of Ministers, Addis Ababa, 1973 May (Box C4., Folder 37.4.2)
        - 21st Ordinary Session (Box C4., Folder 37.4.3)
          - Decisions
          - Secretary-General’s Report on the Working of the Executive Secretariat of the Co-ordination Committee for the Liberation of Africa
          - Note - Presenting the Report of the Administrative Secretary-General
        - 10th Anniversary (Box C4., Folder 37.4.4)
          - Report by ANC delegates of the 10th Anniversary Summits, Addis Ababa and the 10th Ordinary OAU Session of the Heads of State and Governments